<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>lldb on Reboot and Shine</title><link>https://werat.dev/tags/lldb/</link><description>Recent content in lldb on Reboot and Shine</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><lastBuildDate>Tue, 23 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://werat.dev/tags/lldb/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Blazing fast expression evaluation for C++ in LLDB</title><link>https://werat.dev/blog/blazing-fast-expression-evaluation-for-c-in-lldb/</link><pubDate>Tue, 23 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://werat.dev/blog/blazing-fast-expression-evaluation-for-c-in-lldb/</guid><description>Expression evaluation is an integral part of any modern debugger. It allows the user to inspect the program state using the familiar syntax of the target language, as well as perform modifications to the target process (if the side-effects are allowed). If you have ever used command-line debuggers, you&amp;rsquo;re probably familiar with it via commands like print/call in GDB or expr/p in LLDB. It is also used extensively by the IDEs to implement typical UI workflows: Immediate Window, Watch Window, hovering over a variables, custom data visualizers (see NatVis), etc.</description></item><item><title>Debugging LLDB with source stepping</title><link>https://werat.dev/blog/debugging-lldb-with-source-stepping/</link><pubDate>Sun, 11 Oct 2020 18:35:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://werat.dev/blog/debugging-lldb-with-source-stepping/</guid><description>Sometimes you want to (or need to) debug a program that you didn&amp;rsquo;t build yourself and you don&amp;rsquo;t even know how exactly it was built. Depending on the specifics of your setup that could mean many different things:
Built on a build farm, running on a production server/container Installed via apt or similar, running locally &amp;hellip; This post is inspired by my experience of debugging LLDB. Debugging the debugger is always interesting and tricky, even without the additional difficulties like trying to get the source stepping to work :)</description></item></channel></rss>