<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Posts on Reboot and Shine</title><link>https://werat.dev/posts/</link><description>Recent content in Posts on Reboot and Shine</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><lastBuildDate>Mon, 28 Jun 2021 13:35:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://werat.dev/posts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Running benchmarks for Pull Requests via GitHub Actions</title><link>https://werat.dev/blog/running-benchmarks-for-pull-requests-via-github-actions/</link><pubDate>Mon, 28 Jun 2021 13:35:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://werat.dev/blog/running-benchmarks-for-pull-requests-via-github-actions/</guid><description>Benchmarks are often underestimated and don&amp;rsquo;t get the same attention as tests. However &amp;ldquo;performance is a feature&amp;rdquo; and when something is not tested it might as well be just broken. If the performance is not measured/tracked regressions are inevitable.
Modern tooling makes it really easy to write benchmarks. Some languages have built-in support, for example, Rust comes with cargo bench (docs) and Go has go test -bench (docs). For C++ there is google/benchmark &amp;ndash; not as streamlined as having it built into the language infrastructure, but still definitely worth the effort.</description></item><item><title>Blazing fast expression evaluation for C++ in LLDB</title><link>https://werat.dev/blog/blazing-fast-expression-evaluation-for-c-in-lldb/</link><pubDate>Tue, 23 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://werat.dev/blog/blazing-fast-expression-evaluation-for-c-in-lldb/</guid><description>Expression evaluation is an integral part of any modern debugger. It allows the user to inspect the program state using the familiar syntax of the target language, as well as perform modifications to the target process (if the side-effects are allowed). If you have ever used command-line debuggers, you&amp;rsquo;re probably familiar with it via commands like print/call in GDB or expr/p in LLDB. It is also used extensively by the IDEs to support typical UI workflows: Immediate Window, Watch Window, hovering over a variable, custom data visualizers (see NatVis), etc.</description></item><item><title>Debugging LLDB with source stepping</title><link>https://werat.dev/blog/debugging-lldb-with-source-stepping/</link><pubDate>Sun, 11 Oct 2020 18:35:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://werat.dev/blog/debugging-lldb-with-source-stepping/</guid><description>Sometimes you want to (or need to) debug a program that you didn&amp;rsquo;t build yourself and you don&amp;rsquo;t even know how exactly it was built. Depending on the specifics of your setup that could mean many different things:
Built on a build farm, running on a production server/container Installed via apt or similar, running locally &amp;hellip; This post is inspired by my experience of debugging LLDB. Debugging the debugger is always interesting and tricky, even without the additional difficulties like trying to get the source stepping to work :)</description></item><item><title>Happy ssh agent forwarding for tmux/screen</title><link>https://werat.dev/blog/happy-ssh-agent-forwarding/</link><pubDate>Sat, 04 Feb 2017 11:55:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://werat.dev/blog/happy-ssh-agent-forwarding/</guid><description>If you often use ssh+tmux combination and ssh keys forwarding, you&amp;rsquo;ve definitely been in an unpleasant situation:
connect to some remote machine via ssh and create a tmux session use it happily detach from tmux and disconnect from server connect again (e.g. next day) and attach to the tmux session push something to git (or connect to another server)&amp;hellip; &amp;hellip; Permission denied (publickey). Let&amp;rsquo;s discuss why this is happening.</description></item></channel></rss>